The untold story of his final revolution
Che: Part Two is a drama, history, war film directed by Steven Soderbergh.
Seven years after his triumph in Cuba, Che winds up in Bolivia, where he
tries to ignite the same revolutionary fires as before.
Ernesto Che Guevara, played by Benicio del Toro.
Moisés Guevara, played by Carlos Bardem.
Fidel Castro, played by Demián Bichir.
President René Barrientos, played by Joaquim de Almeida.
Pacho (Alberto Fernández Montes de Oca), played by Pablo Durán.
Ciro Algarañaz, played by Eduard Fernández.
Che is a two-part 2008 epic biographical film about the Argentine Marxist
revolutionary Ernesto "Che" Guevara, directed by Steven Soderbergh.
Rather than follow a standard chronological order, the films offer an oblique
series of interspersed moments along the overall timeline.
Part One is titled The Argentine and focuses on the Cuban Revolution from the landing of Fidel Castro, Guevara, and other
revolutionaries in Cuba to their successful toppling of Fulgencio Batista's dictatorship two years later.
Part Two is titled Guerrilla and focuses on Guevara's attempt
to bring revolution to Bolivia and his demise.
Both parts are shot in a cinéma vérité style, but each has different
approaches to linear narrative, camerawork and the visual look.
It stars Benicio del Toro as Guevara, with an ensemble cast that includes Demián Bichir, Rodrigo Santoro, Santiago Cabrera, Franka Potente, Julia Ormond, Vladimir Cruz,
Marc-André Grondin, Lou Diamond Phillips, Joaquim de Almeida, Édgar Ramírez, Yul Vazquez, Unax Ugalde, Alfredo De Quesada, Jordi Mollá, Matt Damon, and Oscar Isaac.
Filmmaker Terrence Malick originally worked on a screenplay limited to
Guevara's attempts to start a revolution in Bolivia.
When financing fell through, Malick left the project, and
Soderbergh subsequently agreed to direct the film.
He realized that there was no context for Guevara's actions in Bolivia and decided that his participation in
the Cuban Revolution and his appearance at the United Nations in 1964 should also be depicted.
Peter Buchman was hired to write the screenplay — the script was so long that Soderbergh decided to
divide the film into two parts: one chronicling Cuba, the other depicting Bolivia.
Soderbergh shot the installments back-to-back starting at the beginning of July 2007, with Guerrilla
first in Spain for 39 days, and The Argentine shot in Puerto Rico and Mexico for 39 days.
Che was screened as a single film at the 2008 Cannes Film Festival.
Del Toro won the Best Actor Award, and the film
received mostly positive reviews.
IFC Films, which holds all North American rights, initially released the combined film for one week on 12
December 2008 in New York City and Los Angeles to qualify for the year's Academy Awards.
Strong box office performance led to the "special roadshow edition" being
extended in NYC and LA, and later expanded into additional markets.
It was released as two separate films, titled Che Part 1: The Argentine and
Che Part 2: Guerrilla, and further distribution followed.
The Independent Film Channel released the films via video on demand
and on Region 1 DVD exclusively from Blockbuster.
As a whole, Che grossed US$40.9 million worldwide,
against a budget of US$58 million.
The film explores themes of hero, central intelligence
agency (cia), cuba, biography, che guevara.
The tone is emotional.